Guide to the William Alpha Cooper Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
William Alpha Cooper papers
1892-1938
SC0008
Cooper, William Alpha, 1868-1939.
3 Linear feet
Correspondence, school notes, manuscripts and publications.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Cooper estate, 1963.
The papers of William A. Cooper came to the Stanford Collection from the Cooper home on the campus. There appears to have been a large quantity of papers at one time as evidenced by the papers still in existence. Mr. Gorham, who acquired the papers for the Library, reported that he was called to the Cooper house and shown to the attic which was covered with papers. He "swept up" what was there and brought it to the Stanford Collection. The second wife of Dr. Cooper was the last occupant of the house. Presumably, as we are led to believe, a maid destroyed much of what was in the attic and would have destroyed the rest had she had time to get at it.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Separated Materials
Two minutes books pertaining to the Classical Club of Stanford University have been removed and added to the proper place in the Archives. These appear to have been in the possession of Grosvenor Cooper, son of William.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of German at Stanford (1901-1934; emeritus, 1934-1939).
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, school notes, manuscripts and publications.
Access Terms
Cooper, William Alpha, 1868-1939.; Goebel, Julius.; Morgan, Bayard.; Philological Association of the Pacific Coast.; Stanford University. Department of German Studies. Faculty.
Collection Contents
- Papers (Box 1)
  - SMALL VEST POCKET NOTEBOOK "MY TRIP ABROAD", 1922 (Box 1)
  - SMALL VEST POCKET NOTEBOOK WRITTEN IN AND ENGLISH ON A VARIETY OF SUBJECTS.GERMAN (Box 1)
  - SMALL NOTEBOOK USED BY COOPER AT MARIETTA COLLEGE IN 1892. (Box 1)
  - RECORD BOOK, "LIST OF BOOKS IN MY PRIVATE LIBRARY MADE JULY, 1904." (Box 1)
  - NOTEBOOK, "NOTES TAKEN IN THE LIBRARY OF THE GOETHE-GESELLSCHAFT, 1908." (Box 1)
  - NOTEBOOK, "VOL. A NOTES AND SKET CHES OF EARLY EXPERIENCES AND IMPRESSIONS." (Box 1)
  - THE STANFORD NOTE BOOK #5. MISC. NOTES. (Box 1)
  - NOTE BOOK, "DAILY EXPENSES, 1912-1920 (Box 1)
  - NOTE BOOK, "BIBLIOGRAPHICAL NOTES ON GOETHE'S LIFE AND WORKS" (Box 1)
  - NOTE BOOK, "THESES, ORATIONS AND ESSAYS WRITTEN IN JUNIOR YEAR BY W. A. COOPER, MARIETTA" (Box 1)
  - INTERLEAVED COPY OF "TASSO" WITH HANDWRITTEN NOTES BY W. A. COOPER. (Box 1)
  - INTERLEAVED COPY OF GOETHE'S COLLECTED WORKS WITH NOTES BY W. A. COOPER. 2 VOLS. (Box 1)
  - STUDENT NOTEBOOKS OF ANNA M. TIETJEN FOR GERMAN 18A AND 18B. (Box 1)
  - GERMAN-AHERICAN STUDENT EXCHANGE, 1926-7. A-G. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - GERMAN-AMERICAN STUDENT EXCHANGE, 1926-7. H-Z. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - COOPER CORRESPONDENCE. 1916-17. A-N. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - COOPER CORRESPONDENCE. 1916-17. P-Z. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - GERMAN DEPARTMENT CORRESPONDENCE. 1917-1920. L-Z. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - LETTERS TO MRS. COOPER. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - CORRESPONDENCE W.A. COOPER. MISC. 1917-1938. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - CORRESPONDENCE W.A. COOPER. 1-ITSC. 1936-1938. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - W.A. COOPER LIBEL ACTION AGAINST THE LOS ANGELES TIMES. 1917. (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - HITLER's AWARD TO W .A. COOPER, 1938. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - MISC. CLIPPINGS, W.A. COOPER. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - NOTES ON GOETHE. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - MISC. NOTES IN GERMAN. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - NOTES ON DAS NIBELUNGELIED. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - MISC. NOTES. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - MISC. NOTES PROBABLY ON GOETHE. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - REPRINTS (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - MSS. COLLEGIATE TRAINING OF HIGH SCHOOL TEACHERS OF GERMAN. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - NOTFS ON THOMAS MANN. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - GERMAN VOCABULARY. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - MSS. SOME SUGGESTIONS FOR THE STUDY OF RECENT GERMAN LITERATURE. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - MSS. THE JUNIOR YEAR IN MUNICH. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - MSS. GEm-tAN ACADEMIC EXCHANGES. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - MSS. OLD AND NEW AQUAINTANCES IN GERMANY. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - GESCHICHTLICHE DICHTUNG. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - MSS. EUIDGY TO MRS. STILLMAN. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - MSS. ROMANTIK. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - MSS. DIE DEUTCHE DICHTUNG UND DIE WELTLITERATUR (1890-1918). (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - THE GOEBEL CASE, 1905-6. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - COHMITTEE ON SUHMER QUARTER STUDENTS, 1924. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - MSS. THE GERMAN INFLATION OF 1922. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - MSS. MODERN LANGUAGE TEACHING: BUSINESS OR CALLING? (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - MSS. GOETHE'S TASSO. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - MSS. PORTIONS OF A MSS. ON TASSO. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - MSS. GOETHE'S CONCEETION OF A POET'S CALLING. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - MISC. PAPERS, DIPLCMAS, SCHOOL CARDS, ETC. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - MISC. INCOMING LETTERS, TELEGRAMS (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - LETTEI5 TO MRS. COOPER FROM W.A. COOPER, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - LETTERS TO DR. JULIUS PETERSEN FROM W.A. COOPER, 1932-1934. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - LETTERS TO TILL, CHRISTINE FROM W.A. COPPER. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - 1931-34 (WEIMAR-JENA SUMMER COLLEGE). LETTERS TO MORSBACH, DR. PHIL A., DEUTCHER AKADEMISCHER AUSTAUSCHDIENST. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - SUMMER EMPLOYMENT 1918 IN FARM OR DEFENSE (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - INDUSTRY (COOPER, STANFORD ENROLLMENT OFFICER OF THE U.S. PUBLIC SERVICE RESERVE). COOPER, W.A. 1916-18. PHILOLOGICAL ASSOC. (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - OF THE PACIFIC COAST. COOPER, W.A. 1916-18. OF THE PACIFIC COAST. PHILOLOGICAL ASSOC. (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - COOPER, W.A. 1916-18. PHILOGICAL ASSOC. OF THE PACIFIC COAST. (3). (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - W. A. COOPER. VARIOUS TYPESCRIPTS, INCLUDING SHORT AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF EXPERIENCES IN GERMANY. (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - MORGAN, BAYARD Q. CORRESPONDENCE WITH, 1928-1934 ( CONCERNED WITH MORGAN FILLING COOPER'S PLACE WHEN COOPER RETIRES ) (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - DEUTSCHE AKADEMIE IM MUNICH 1932-1934. (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - PETSCH, ROBERT. CORRESPONDENCE WITH, 1928-1934. (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - GRAF, H.G. CORRESPONDENCE WITH, 1920-1927. (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - COOPER LETTERS, 1931. COOPER IN EUROPE AND REPORTS TO HIS DEPARTHENT AND FRIENDS. (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - TYPESCRIPT OF THE PROGRESSIVE TEACHER. (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - VARIOUS PUBLICATIONS OF W.A. COOPER, INCLUDING DER BIBLIOTHEKAR ED. BY COOPER, AMERICAN BOOK COMPANY, 1902. (Box 6, Folder 37)